updated: 5/23 Chad McKell

# **ABOUT**

Position Ph.D. Candidate, UC San Diego

Affiliations Center for Visual Computing, Department of Music

Address 9500 Gilman Dr MC 0099

La Jolla, CA 92093-0099

Phone +1 661 289 4215 Email cmckell@ucsd.edu Website chadmckell.com

Research My research covers mathematical modeling and numerical simulation of acoustic

systems. I am especially interested in differential geometric modeling for sound simulation and its applications in computational audio, computer graphics, and auditory biophysics. Current projects include boundary modeling for acoustic wave propagation simulations; sound source modeling for computer animation; and physical simulation of

musical instruments and the human cochlea.

## **EDUCATION**

| 9/19-       | University of California San Diego, Ph.D. in Computer Music               |  |  |
|-------------|---|--|--|
|             | GPA: 4.0. Dissertation: Geometric Boundary Modeling for Wave Simulations. |  |  |
|             | Advisors: Albert Chern (CSE) and Miller Puckette (Music).                 |  |  |
| 0/16 10/17  | University of Edinburgh MC in Accepting and Music Technology              |  |  |
| 9/16-10/17  | University of Edinburgh, M.S. in Acoustics and Music Technology           |  |  |
| 8/09-12/15  | Wake Forest University, M.S. in Physics                                   |  |  |
| 6/02 - 8/09 | Brigham Young University, B.S. in Biophysics                              |  |  |

### **EMPLOYMENT**

| <b>Diego</b> , Teaching Assistant/Researcher (Music)     |
|--|
| , Research Intern/Student Researcher (Acoustics)         |
| cs, R&D Scientist (Acoustics)                            |
| Software Developer (Audio DSP)                           |
| ation Researcher (Acoustics)                             |
| ting Software Development Engineer in Test (QA)          |
| <b>School of the Arts</b> , Adjunct Instructor (Physics) |
| hing Assistant (Physics)                                 |
| Tutorial Lab Assistant (Physics)                         |
| Research Assistant (Philosophy)                          |
|  |

## RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

9/19— University of California San Diego, Ph.D. Student/Candidate (Acoustics)

La Jolla, California. Research topics: computational acoustics, differential geometry, numerical simulation. Dissertation summary: develop differential geometric methods for modeling boundaries in wave-based virtual acoustic simulations. Committee members: Albert Chern (co-chair), Miller Puckette (co-chair), Melvin Leok, Shahrokh Yadegari, Stefan Bilbao (Univ. of Edinburgh), and Sebastian Prepeliță (Meta).

#### RESEARCH ACTIVITIES CONT.

8/21–3/22 Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern/Student Researcher (Acoustics)

La Jolla, California. Research topics: binaural audio, numerical simulation, parallel programming, discrete complex analysis. Research summary: conducted computational acoustics research for virtual and augmented reality devices. Supervisor: Sebastian

Prepeliță. Team Lead: Ravish Mehra.

7/18–7/19 Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist (Acoustics)

Culpeper, Virginia. Research topics: underwater acoustics, matched filtering, sparse estimation, beamforming. Research summary: developed physics-based signal processing

algorithms for naval sonar systems. Team Lead: Jonathan Botts.

1/17–8/17 University of Edinburgh, Master's Student (Acoustics)

Edinburgh, Scotland. Research topics: speech acoustics, elastodynamics, numerical simulation. Thesis summary: developed physics-based numerical simulations of structural vibrations for haptic feedback devices. My thesis was partially funded by Lofelt, a Berlin-based haptic feedback company acquired by Meta in 2022. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.

1/10–9/13 Wake Forest University, Master's Student (Physics)

Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Research topics: optical trapping, laser characterization, fluid dynamics. Thesis summary: implemented transverse nanoparticle tracking in

surface-isolated laser traps. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

8/07–8/09 Brigham Young University, Undergraduate Student (Biophysics)

Provo, Utah. Research topics: structural biology, scanning probe microscopy. Research summary: studied the effect of anesthetics on lipid bilayer structure using atomic force

microscopy. Advisor: David Busath.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### As Instructor

| τ | J. | N | $\mathbf{CS}$ | $\mathbf{S}\mathbf{A}$ |
|---|----|---|---------------|------------------------|
|   |    |   |               |                        |

SCI 1100 General Physics. Fall 2012 (1 term).

### As TA

| $\underline{\mathbf{UCSD}}$ |  |
|-----------------------------|--|
| MUS 5                       | Sound in Time. Spring 2020 (1 term).                   |
| MUS 6                       | Electronic Music. Fall 2020 (1 term).                  |
| MUS 15                      | Popular Music: David Bowie. Winter 2021 (1 term).      |
| MUS 15                      | Popular Music: Video Game Music. Winter 2020 (1 term). |
| MUS 171                     | Computer Music I. Winter 2022 (1 term).                |
| MUS 172                     | Computer Music II. 2021–2022 (2 terms).                |
|                             |  |
| $\underline{\mathbf{WFU}}$  |  |
| PHY 113                     | General Physics I (Mechanics). 2009–2011 (4 terms).    |
| PHY 114                     | General Physics II (E&M). Fall 2010 (1 term).          |

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE CONT.

## As Tutor

| $\underline{\mathbf{BYU}}$ |  |
|----------------------------|--|
| PHSCS 105                  | General Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).          |
| PHSCS 106                  | General Physics 2 (E&M). Winter 2009 (1 term).               |
| PHSCS 121                  | Principles of Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).    |
| PHSCS 123                  | Principles of Physics 2 (Waves/Thermo). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms). |
| PHSCS 220                  | Principles of Physics 3 (E&M). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms)           |

## PH.D. COURSEWORK

| CSE 167  | Computer Graphics I (Jürgen Schulze)                 |
|----------|--|
| CSE 169  | Computer Animation—audit (Steve Rotenberg)           |
| CSE 274  | Discrete Differential Geometry (Albert Chern)        |
| CSE 291  | Physical Simulation—audit (Chern/Rotenberg)          |
| CSE 299  | Differential Geometry Research (Albert Chern)        |
| MUS 206  | Spatialization (Shahrokh Yadegari)                   |
| MUS 206  | Deep Learning for Music Generation (Shlomo Dubnov)   |
| MUS 206  | Computational Acoustic Modeling (Tamara Smyth)       |
| MUS 270A | Digital Audio Processing (Tamara Smyth)              |
| MUS 270B | Analysis of Musical Sound (Miller Puckette)          |
| MUS 270C | Compositional Algorithms (Miller Puckette)           |
| MUS 270D | Advanced Projects in Computer Music (Puckette/Smyth) |
| MUS 298  | Virtual Acoustics Research (Puckette/Smyth/Dubnov)   |
| MUS 298  | Differential Geometry Research (Miller Puckette)     |

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Manuscripts in Progress

(1) C. McKell, M. Nabizadeh, S. Wang, and A. Chern, "Wave simulations in infinite spacetime". Under review.

Simulating wave propagation on an infinite domain has been a long-standing computational challenge. Conventional approaches to this problem only produce wave simulations on a small subset of the infinite domain. Using the fact that wave propagation on an infinite Minkowski spacetime is equivalent to wave propagation on a bounded Minkowski spacetime under a Kelvin-like transformation, we simulate wave propagation on the entire infinite domain using a finite discretization of the bounded domain with no additional loss of accuracy from the transformation.

(2) C. McKell, Geometric Boundary Modeling for Wave Simulations. Ph.D. Dissertation, University of California San Diego, Department of Music. Defese planned for Spring 2024. (Advisors: Albert Chern and Miller Puckette).

I introduce a novel differential geometric framework for handling boundaries arising from unbounded spacetime domains and curved obstacle boundaries. I show that the scalar wave equation is conformally invariant under Kelvin transformations in Minkowski spacetime, but the difficulties associated with unbounded domains and curved obstacle boundaries are not. I use this fact to transform unbounded domain problems into bounded domain problems and curved obstacle boundaries into flat boundaries. The transformed problems can then be easily solved using standard numerical methods. Compared to conventional approaches for solving these boundary problems, my framework achieves higher efficiency without losing any accuracy.

#### PUBLICATIONS CONT.

### **Journal Articles**

(3) C. McKell and K. Bonin, "Optical corral using a standing-wave Bessel beam," *Journal of the Optical Society of America B*, Vol. 35, No. 8, 1910–1920, 2018.

## Conference Proceedings

(4) C. McKell, "Sonification of optically-ordered Brownian motion," In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference (ICMC), Utrecht, Netherlands, September 2016.

#### Master's Theses

- (5) C. McKell, Real-time physical modeling for haptic feedback rendering. Final Project Dissertation, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. (Advisor: Stefan Bilbao).
- (6) C. McKell, Finite-difference simulations of speech with wall vibration losses. Special Project Dissertation, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. (Advisor: Stefan Bilbao).
- (7) C. McKell, Confinement and tracking of Brownian particles in a Bessel beam standing wave. Master's Thesis, Wake Forest University, Department of Physics, 2015. (Advisor: Keith Bonin).

## **Technical Reports**

(8) C. McKell, H. Conley, and D. Busath, "AFM study of structural changes in supported planar DPPC bilayers containing general anesthetic isoflurane," Brigham Young University, Paper 827, 2010.